<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God and the king: or A dialogue shewing that our souereigne Lord King Iames beeing immediate vnder God within his dominions, doth rightfully claime whatsoeuer is required by the oath of allegiance</title>
            <title>Deus &amp; rex. English</title>
            <author>Mocket, Richard, 1577-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14419A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836969</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836969</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04305)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1384:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God and the king: or A dialogue shewing that our souereigne Lord King Iames beeing immediate vnder God within his dominions, doth rightfully claime whatsoeuer is required by the oath of allegiance</title>
                  <title>Deus &amp; rex. English</title>
                  <author>Mocket, Richard, 1577-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2]+ leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by C. Legge] by his Maiesties speciall priuiledge and commaund,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Mocket, Richard.  Deus et rex.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A fragment.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <p>GOD and the KING: OR, <hi>A DIALOGVE</hi> ſhewing that our Soueraigne Lord <hi>King</hi> IAMES <hi>beeing immediate</hi> vnder God within his DOMINIONS, <hi>Doth rightfully claime whatſoeuer</hi> is required by the Oath of ALLEGIANCE.</p>
            <p>CAMBRIDGE, Imprinted by his Maieſties ſpeciall <hi>priuiledge and commaund.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <head>The Contents of this <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THe occaſions and cheife ende of the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: from pag. 1. vnto pag. 25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſpeciall heads and branches of the Oath of Allegiance: from <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> pag. 3<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The principall grounds of the Oath of Allegeance, are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and eſtabliſht, as</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That our Soueraigne Lord King IAMES hath no Superiour beſides God, vnto whome hee is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb facs="tcp:1271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
ſubiect within his Dominions:</hi> from pag. 31. vnto pag. 65.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the bond of Allegiance from his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects vnto him as their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Lord, is inuiolable, and cannot by any meanes be diſſolued:</hi>from pag. 65. vnto pag. 93.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="fragmentary_dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <sp>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Law,</hi> bée neglected for ſauing the life of a King, vpon whom ſo many liues depend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that neither the<hi>ſeale of Confeſſion</hi> doth frée vs from any part of the duties of allegiance vnto our <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philalethes:</speaker>
               <p>If the bond of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance from ſubiects vnto their Prince is ſo inuiolable, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, no not <hi>the ſeale of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> can diſſolue it; is there no meanes to ſtay the fury of a <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Commander,</hi> If he ſhould be ſo Tyrannous, and profane, as to endeauour to oppreſſe the whole Church at once, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to extinguiſh the light of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1271:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
               <p>obedience vnto their Soueraigne, is grounded vpon the law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; beginning with our firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: For as wee bée borne <hi>Sonnes,</hi> ſo we are borne <hi>Subiects;</hi> his <hi>Sonnes,</hi> from whoſe loynes; his <hi>Subiects</hi> in whoſe Dominions wee are borne. The ſame duties of ſubiects are alſo enioyned by the morall law, and particularly (as you ſhewed in the verie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance vnto this out Conference) in the fift commandement, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Father and thy Mother:</hi>where, as wée are required to honour the <hi>Fathers</hi> of priuate families, ſo much more the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of our country and the whole Kingdome. And as the Biſhop of Rome cannot diſpenſe with theſe lawes impoſing vpon vs obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto his Maieſtie, ſo neither with the oath wée take to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in this obedience. When <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, <hi>I haue<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſworne that I will keepe thy righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1271:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:1271:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
               <p>obedience vnto excommunicated Princes: beſides, excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (according to the doctrine of the<note n="e" place="margin">Aquin. in ſup. que 23. Tolet Inſt. Sacerd. l: 1. c. 9.</note> Romaniſts themſelues) doth not frée a ſeruant from obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto his Maſter, or a ſonne vnto his Father. And Kings are as <hi>Maſters,</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> as <hi>Seruants;</hi> for <hi>ſo Dauid</hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Saul</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.11.</note> his <hi>Maſter,</hi> and ſtileth himſelfe his <note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam.</note> 
                  <hi>Seruant:</hi> Kinges are as<note n="h" place="margin">2 Chro. 29. <hi>Debora</hi> a mother in Iſrael. Iudg. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Fathers,</hi> and ſubiects as<hi>Sonnes;</hi> for ſo King <hi>Ezechias</hi> was a <hi>Father</hi> ouer the<hi>Fathers</hi> of his people, euen the Prieſts, and therefore much more ouer the reſt of his ſubiects. As then excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication doth not diſſolue the bond of duty betwéene <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Sonnes,</hi> of ſeruice betwéene<hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Seruants,</hi> no more doth it the bond of fidelity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene <hi>Princes</hi> and their <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</hi> And ſo at length I haue <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oued vnto you, that neither ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:1271:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
               <p>nor the Epiſcopall Acts of <hi>diſpenſation,</hi> and <hi>excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and ſo in effect, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can frée ſubiects from their fidelitie and allegiance vnto their Prince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philalethes.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing! The <hi>ſeale</hi> of <hi>confeſſion</hi> doth at leaſt in part free ſome ſubiects from ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall duties of obedience vnto their Soueraigne; as Prieſts from reuealing treaſons and Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which they know, as <hi>Ghoſtly Fathers,</hi> from the penitent. For if conſpiracies or treaſons bee known vnto a Prieſt in confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the bond thereof doth bind him to conceale it,<note n="b" place="margin">Aquin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in ſup. q. 11. Art. 1.</note> becauſe they are knowne vnto him as vnto GOD, whoſe Vicar he is in hearing the humble confeſſions of repentant Sinners.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theodidactus.</speaker>
               <p>If Prieſts in confeſſions doe vnderſtand of treaſons and other <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>mous <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:1271:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale as GOD, and as his Vicars; then they are to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate GOD, whom they would repreſent, in the diſcouering of theſe greiuous crimes. For GOD alwaies doth after a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous manner, and (as it were) by his owne immediate finger bring to light crying ſinnes, when they are done in ſecret, and for a time are in wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>Did he not by the birds of the aire detect the murder of<note place="margin">Ibycus vt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijt, vi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fuit alti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>gens. A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Iby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus?</hi> And becauſe the perſons of Princes are more ſacred then the perſons of priuate men, GOD hath made a ſpeciall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Kings,</hi> by the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Heauen</hi> (that is) after a ſtrange and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous manner, if by ordinary meanes they ſhall not be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And therefore ſome Prieſts of France haue detected intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1271:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
of treaſon, onely in thought, heard by them in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and the Authors of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments haue béene puniſhed with death. A<note n="f" place="margin">Bodin. lib. 2. <hi>di Repub. ca.</hi> 5.</note> Gentleman of Normandy in France confeſſed vnto a <hi>Frier Minor,</hi> that hée had once a reſolution to murther <hi>King <hi>Francis,</hi>
                  </hi> and that hée repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his wicked purpoſe. The Frier gaue him abſolution, but reuealed his wicked purpoſe vnto the King: and after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation had thereof in the Parliament of Paris, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was executed; and the Frier not puniſhed with any cenſure of the Church for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ents</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ing their ſinnes, not to conceale theſe ſinnes if they bee enormous and dangerous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the publike ſtate; but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their commiſſion; <hi>(whoſe ſinnes ye remit, they are remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Ioh. 20.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1271:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
to declare vnto them the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſinnes as they are offences onely againſt GOD, and before his heauenly Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philalethes.</speaker>
               <p>But the <hi>law of the Church</hi> commandeth Prieſts to conceale all ſuch ſinnes as come vnto their Knowledge by way of Confeſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theodidactus.</speaker>
               <p>This Lawe of the Church is but the Law of Pope<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, cited in the decretalls (for he is the moſt ancient Author that the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts can alledge for their <hi>ſeale of Confeſſion:)</hi> But were it a Law of the whole Church, it is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1271:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
béene then in his fulneſſe of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, could hee haue diſpenſed with this oath? And ſo if any now, by the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſweare to kéepe Gods righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>not committing adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or of <hi>honouring their Parents, and Magiſtrates;</hi> hee cannot frée them from this oath: but if wee violate both theſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we are as well <hi>Rebels,</hi> as
<hi>Adulterers.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philalethes.</speaker>
               <p>Are not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications of the Biſhoppe of Rome of more force to looſe the bond of allegiance, then his diſpenſations?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theodidactus.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe likewiſe haue no power to worke this effect. Excommunication vpon a contempt vnto the Church doth not make a man worſe then an <hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">d</hi> Ethnike:</hi> but you haue heard that both S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S.<hi>Paul</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhort vs to be ſubiect vnto heathen, and Ethnicke Princes; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:1271:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
they doe<hi>labour</hi> to effect ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous an impiety, the onely meanes we haue to appeaſe their fury is <hi>ſerious repentance</hi> for our ſinnes, which haue brought this chaſtiſement vpon vs; and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayer vnto GOD, who guideth <hi>the hearts of Princes like riuers of waters.</hi> You know how before the comming of <hi>CHRIST</hi>the viſible Church was onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Iewes; and that whiles they were Captiues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Perſian Monarches, <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus</hi> at the inſtigation of <hi>Haman</hi> ſent forth a decrée <hi>to<note n="a" place="margin">Eſter. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> deſtroy them all both young &amp; old, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and women in one day. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:1271:8"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Eſter. cap. 4.</note> great ſorrow amongſt them, and faſting and weeping, many ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſacke-cloth and aſhes,</hi> to humble them-ſelues vnder the mightie hand of GOD for their ſinnes, and to auert his wrath hanging ouer their heads, by the crueltie of ſo bloody a Tyrant.</p>
               <p>And the ancient Chriſtians, vpon the like occaſions, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe Iewes. For when they were threatned by <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, with an vtter extinction of<hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> they hindred and <note n="c" place="margin">Nazianz. ora. 1. in Iulian.</note> 
                  <hi>repreſſed him with their teares, hauing this onely remedie againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuter.</hi> If any therefore are oppreſſed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:1271:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
the ſinnes of offenders, are the ſtrength of Tyrants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philalethes.</speaker>
               <p>To be freed from Tyrannie and oppreſſion in this world, is a temporall benefit: and many times GOD hearkneth not vnto our praiers for tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefits. How then are faithfull and loyall ſubiects to comfort them-ſelues, againſt the preſſures of mercileſſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theodidactus.</speaker>
               <p>Their onely comfort in this caſe, is that which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> long ſince miniſtred vnto them. <hi>The rod of ſinners</hi> (ſaith hee, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of wicked Maſters <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>  
                     <hi>but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>tim<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ill come when one GOD ſhall be acknowledged: The time will come, when one CHRIST, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in his brightneſſe, ſhall gather before him all Nations;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1271:7"/>
                        <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
and ſeuer them, as a Paſtor ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth his Goates from the ſheep, and place his ſheepe vpon his right hand, and his Goates vpon his left. And then thou ſhalt ſee many ſeruants, <hi>and ſubiects,</hi> amongſt the ſheepe, and many maſters, <hi>and Princes,</hi> amongſt the Goates: and againe many maſters, <hi>and Princes,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sheepe, and many <hi>ſubiects and</hi> Seruants amongſt the Goates.</hi> So when all other helpes and comforts doe fayle diſtreſſed ſubiects; the day of Iudgement, the ende of all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory things will bring an ende</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> GOD ſo to affect the hearts both of <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Subiects,</hi> with a ſerious and frequent cogitation of this laſt Iudgement; that they in Gouerning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe in Obeying,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1271:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
both in all their actions,<note place="margin">De Reg. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacho.</note> and <hi>whatſoeuer they doe,</hi> may (with Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>) haue the voyce of the Archangell alwaies ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in their eares, <hi>Ariſe from the dead, and come vnto iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:1271:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
